Guide to the Paul Newman Scripts and Films
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Paul Newman scripts and films
1956-1989
YCAL MSS 384
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.2
(8 boxes) + 14 film reels
The collection consists of scripts and film reels documenting aspects of the film and theater career of Paul Newman. Scripts include annotated typescript drafts of screenplays (annotations seem to be those of Newman) for films, including The Color of Money, that shed light on Newman's creative process as an actor and his contributions to the screenplay revision process, as well as bound typescript copies of screenplays with photographs that document the production of certain films, such as Cool Hand Luke. Also found are screenplays for films directed by Newman, including Rachel, Rachel, and scripts for plays in which he starred, including C. C. Pyle and the Bunion Derby. Film reels include recordings and outtakes related to the making of various motion pictures and the television program "The Battler," in which Newman starred.
Newman, Paul, 1925-2008
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale Drama Library, 2007.
Custodial History
Donated to the Yale Drama Library by Paul Newman, 1985-1991.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Containers 9-22 (film reels): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Paul Newman (1925-2008)
Paul Newman was an award-winning actor and director who starred in over fifty major motion picture films. He graduated from the Yale School of Drama in 1954.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of scripts and film reels documenting aspects of the film and theater career of Paul Newman. Scripts include annotated typescript drafts of screenplays(annotations seem to be those of Newman) for films, including The Color of Money, that shed light on Newman's creative process as an actor and his contributions to the screenplay revision process, as well as bound typescript copies of screenplays with photographs that document the production of certain films, such as Cool Hand Luke. Also found are screenplays for films directed by Newman, including Rachel, Rachel, and scripts for plays in which he starred, including C. C. Pyle and the Bunion Derby. Film reels include recordings and outtakes related to the making of various motion pictures and the television program "The Battler," in which Newman starred.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Scripts, 1958-1989. II. Film Reels, 1956-1981.
Motion picture actors and actresses -- United States -- 20th Century; Motion picture producers and directors -- United States -- 20th Century; Motion pictures -- United States -- 20th Century; Audiovisual materials; Motion pictures (visual works); Photographs; Scripts (documents); Screenplays; Actors; Film directors; Newman, Paul, 1925-2008
- Scripts, 1958-1989; Series I; 3.2; (8 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Absence of Malice (1981)
    - Typescript, annotated, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Photocopy, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Blaze (1989), typescript, annotated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - C.C. Pyle and the Bunion Derby, typescript, annotated, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Color of Money (1986)
    - Typescript, annotated, 1985 April (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Second draft, photocopy, annotated, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Revised typescript, annotated, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes cast list and shooting schedule.
    - The Color of Money by Walter Tevis, photocopy, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "The Hustler: 8-Ball" by Darryl Ponicsan (Based on the Novel "The Color of Money" by Walter Tevis), bound typescript, annotated, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Cool Hand Luke (1967), bound typescript with photographs, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - The Effect of Gamma Rays...on the Man-in-The-Moon Marigolds (1980), 1972
    - Second draft, typescript, annotated, including notes, 1971 August 5 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Rehearsal draft, typescript, annotated, 1972 March 14 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Rehearsal draft, photocopy, 1972 March 14 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Fat Man and Little Boy (1989), typescript, annotated, 1988 October 17 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Includes shooting schedule.
  - The Glass Menagerie (1987), typescript, annotated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Harper (1966), bound typescript with photographs (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Harry & Son (1984), annotated typescript, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Hombre (1967), bound typescript with photographs, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Bridge (1990), typescript, annotated, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - The Outrage (1964), typescript, annotated, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Pocket Money (1972), typescript (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Rachel, Rachel (1968)
    - "A Jest of God" (Rachel, Rachel) Workbook, Stewart Stern, For Paul, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 22-23)
      Includes photocopies of draft screenplay, shooting schedule, notes, expense reports, as well as some typescript and manuscript notes.
    - "A Jest of God," final draft, typescript, annotated, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - "A Jest of God," final draft, photocopy, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 25-26)
  - The Secret War of Harry Frigg (1968), bound typescript with photographs, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - The Shadow Box (1980), typescript, annotated, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Sometimes a Great Notion (1970), typescript, annotated (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Sweet Bird of Youth (1962)
    - Typescript, annotated, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Photocopy, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - The Verdict (1982), 1981
    - Typescript, 1891 (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Typescript, annotated, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - WUSA (1970) (formerly "A Hall of Mirrors"), typescript, annotated, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - The Young Philadelphians (1959), typescript, annotated, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 35)
- Film Reels, 1956-1981; Series II; (14 reels)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Containers 9-22 (film reels): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - "The Battler" (1956) (Box 9 Cold Storage)
  - The Drowning Pool (1975), excerpts (Box 10 Cold Storage)
  - Fort Apache the Bronx (1981) (Box 11 Cold Storage)
  - Fort Apache the Bronx (1981) (Box 12 Cold Storage)
  - Fort Apache the Bronx (1981) (Box 13 Cold Storage)
  - Fort Apache the Bronx (1981) (Box 14 Cold Storage)
  - The Making of Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid, 1969 (Box 15 Cold Storage)
  - Quintet (1979) (Box 16 Cold Storage)
  - Quintet (1979) (Box 17 Cold Storage)
  - Quintet (1979) (Box 18 Cold Storage)
  - Slap Shot (1977) (Box 19 Cold Storage)
  - Slap Shot (1977) (Box 20 Cold Storage)
  - Slap Shot (1977) (Box 21 Cold Storage)
  - Slap Shot (1977) (Box 22 Cold Storage)